<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<command id="create-feature-branch"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../commands.xsd">

    <goal><![CDATA[
Create and switch the current checkout to a conventionally named local branch for GitHub issue, OpenSpec, analysis, design, documentation, or implementation work.

## Usage

```text
/create-feature-branch <issue-or-change|type description> [<base-reference>]
```

## Accepted Inputs

- An issue/change identifier, or an explicit branch type and description
- Optional base reference
- Supported branch types: `feat`, `fix`, `docs`, `refactor`, and `chore`
- Preferred branch format: `<type>/<issue-or-change>-<kebab-case-description>` when an issue or OpenSpec change is available, otherwise `<type>/<kebab-case-description>`

## Owning Agent

`@robot-tech-lead`

## Associated Capabilities

- Git branch naming and validation
- GitHub issue and OpenSpec change traceability
- Analysis/design-to-implementation transition
- Safe handling of existing local work
]]></goal>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">Read the repository instructions and resolve the branch type, issue/change identifier, and kebab-case description from the request.</step>
        <step number="2">Prefer GitHub issue or OpenSpec change identifiers for traceable work; for complex architectural changes, keep the branch aligned to the OpenSpec change name.</step>
        <step number="3">Resolve the repository default branch and the current branch.</step>
        <step number="4">Verify the current checkout is `main` or the repository default branch before creating the new branch.</step>
        <step number="5">If the current branch is not `main` or the default branch, stop and ask whether to switch to the default branch, choose a different base, or continue explicitly from the current branch.</step>
        <step number="6">Verify the repository, selected base reference, branch name, and a safe working tree before changing the current checkout.</step>
        <step number="7">Stop if the proposed branch already exists or is checked out in another worktree.</step>
        <step number="8">Create and switch to the conventionally named local branch.</step>
        <step number="9">Report the branch name, base reference, working tree status, and traceability source used to derive the branch.</step>
    </steps>

    <output-format>
        <output-format-list>
            <output-format-item>Created local branch</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Confirmation with the exact branch name and base reference</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Working tree status and any traceability source used for naming</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>A checkout ready for GitHub issue follow-up, OpenSpec artifacts, ADRs, diagrams, documentation, or application code</output-format-item>
        </output-format-list>
    </output-format>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>Stop when uncommitted work could be displaced or mixed into the new branch.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Never discard, stash, reset, or move existing uncommitted changes unless the user explicitly requests that action.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Stop and ask when the current branch is not `main` or the repository default branch.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not overwrite, delete, or force-update an existing branch.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Allow analysis and design artifacts to be committed before application-code implementation.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>The command does not create a commit automatically.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not push or open a pull request automatically.</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</command>
