<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<command id="explore-design"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../commands.xsd">

    <metadata>
        <description>Refine the technical design of an issue or OpenSpec change before implementation.</description>
        <argument-hint>[openspec-change]</argument-hint>
        <model>inherit</model>
        <agent>robot-architect</agent>
        <tools>
            <tools-list>
                <tool>Read</tool>
                <tool>Write</tool>
                <tool>Edit</tool>
                <tool>Bash</tool>
            </tools-list>
        </tools>
    </metadata>

    <goal><![CDATA[
Improve and refine the technical approach for an issue or OpenSpec change after initial specification—with alternatives, trade-offs, compatibility review, rollout controls, and verification strategy—before implementation.

## Usage

```text
/explore-design <issue|openspec-change>
```

## Accepted Inputs

- Issue or user story
- OpenSpec change with unresolved technical approaches or design gaps
- Existing architecture context and constraints
- Relevant requirements, ADRs, or technical notes linked to the issue or change

## Owning Agent

`@robot-architect`

## Associated Skills

- `051-design-two-steps-methods` for every refinement so preparatory work, behavior change, and verification remain explicitly sequenced
- `052-design-hamburger-method` when the scope is broad enough to need smallest-useful vertical slices
- `053-design-simple-rules` when alternatives need ordered design tradeoff evaluation before finalizing the direction
- `054-design-tdd` when testing-related requirements need test-first sequencing and verification-driven refinement
- `055-design-parallel-change` when database migration requirements need expand, migrate, contract sequencing
- `056-design-avoid-breaking-changes` when compatibility surfaces may change during refinement
- `057-design-feature-toggles` when rollout, rollback, compatibility windows, or temporary behavior controls affect the design direction
- `059-design-atdd` as the final alignment gate when an OpenSpec change provides a proposal, specification scenarios, and a task checklist
- `121-java-object-oriented-design`, then `122-java-type-design`, then `123-java-design-patterns` when Java responsibilities, type boundaries, or collaboration decisions affect the refined approach
- `130-java-testing-strategies` when testing strategy, boundary coverage, flakiness, or verification quality affect the refined approach

## Workflow position

Runs after `/create-spec`, not as the first mission in the workflow.
]]></goal>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">Identify the design source, problem, goals, constraints, stakeholders, assumptions, unknowns, success criteria, and recommendation criteria.</step>
        <step number="2">Compare feasible approaches and trade-offs, recording rejected options and risks.</step>
        <step number="3">Recommend a design direction with rationale.</step>
        <step number="4">Describe components, boundaries, interactions, data flow, failure handling, testing strategy, and validation needed before implementation.</step>
        <step number="5">Identify unresolved questions and ADR candidates.</step>
        <step number="6">Refine the existing OpenSpec change when one is provided, without replacing initial OpenSpec authoring owned by `/create-spec`.</step>
        <step number="7">When an OpenSpec change provides an execution goal, acceptance criteria, and a task checklist, invoke `059-design-atdd` as the final read-only alignment gate after approved refinements. Report its evidence-backed `ready` or `changes-requested` outcome.</step>
        <step number="8">For `ready`, continue to the explicit design-approval step without treating the review itself as approval. For `changes-requested`, report every unresolved finding, ask the maintainer how the affected artifacts should be revised, apply only maintainer-approved revisions, and rerun the alignment gate before requesting approval.</step>
    </steps>

    <output-format>
        <output-format-list>
            <output-format-item>Approved design direction</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Alternative and trade-off analysis</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>ADR candidates</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Open questions and assumptions</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Refined OpenSpec change artifacts when applicable</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Evidence-backed ATDD alignment outcome and unresolved findings when reviewable OpenSpec artifacts are provided</output-format-item>
        </output-format-list>
    </output-format>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>Do not implement application code.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not modify source user stories, Gherkin files, ADRs, or OpenAPI files while exploring and refining the design.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not hide material trade-offs or unresolved decisions.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not treat the recommendation as approved until the user confirms it.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not apply `042-planning-openspec`; initial OpenSpec authoring belongs to `/create-spec`.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not apply `059-design-atdd` to issue-only or user-story-only input unless a reviewable OpenSpec proposal, specification scenarios, and task checklist are also supplied.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not report a design direction or OpenSpec change as approved while `059-design-atdd` has unresolved partial, missing, ambiguous, absent, or divergent findings.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not silently add, remove, or rewrite OpenSpec proposals, acceptance criteria, specification scenarios, or tasks in response to alignment findings; apply only maintainer-approved revisions and rerun the review.</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</command>
