<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<command id="update-issue"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../commands.xsd">

    <metadata>
        <description>Update an issue description with structured, evidence-backed content.</description>
        <argument-hint>[issue] [source] [tracker]</argument-hint>
        <model>inherit</model>
        <agent>inherit</agent>
        <tools>
            <tools-list>
                <tool>Read</tool>
                <tool>Bash</tool>
            </tools-list>
        </tools>
    </metadata>

    <goal><![CDATA[
Update an existing project issue description with structured, evidence-backed content.

## Usage

```text
/update-issue <issue> [<source>] [<tracker>]
```

## Accepted Inputs

- Existing GitHub or Jira issue number, key, or URL
- Optional source notes, supporting discussion, user story, acceptance criteria, or file path
- Optional tracker selection: GitHub or Jira

## Owning Agent

`@robot-business-analyst`

## Associated Skills

- `043-planning-github-issues`
- `044-planning-jira`
- `045-planning-azure-devops`
- `014-agile-user-story` when user-story refinement is required
]]></goal>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">Load the current issue description and relevant discussion before drafting changes.</step>
        <step number="2">Confirm the requested update scope and the source material authority.</step>
        <step number="3">Use `014-agile-user-story` when the update needs user-story, acceptance-criteria, or Gherkin-style structure.</step>
        <step number="4">Draft the updated issue body without inventing requirements.</step>
        <step number="5">Present the proposed body before overwriting the existing issue description.</step>
        <step number="6">Update the issue in the selected tracker after approval.</step>
        <step number="7">Report the issue identifier and URL.</step>
    </steps>

    <output-format>
        <output-format-list>
            <output-format-item>Updated structured issue description</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Acceptance criteria or user-story scenario when applicable</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>Updated GitHub/Jira issue reference</output-format-item>
        </output-format-list>
    </output-format>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>Do not invent requirements, acceptance criteria, or comments.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not expose tracker credentials or tokens.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Do not overwrite an issue body without showing the proposed replacement.</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>Preserve relevant existing issue content unless the user explicitly asks to remove it.</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</command>
