<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd">

    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>Non-relational database query best practices</title>
        <description>Use when you need framework-agnostic MongoDB and non-relational database query guidance — document schema design, collection modeling, JSON Schema validation, indexes, aggregation pipelines, query performance, consistency trade-offs, transactions, and operational safety.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a senior database engineer with deep experience in MongoDB, non-relational data modeling, production query performance, and Java application data-access boundaries</role>

    <goal>
        Apply **framework-agnostic** MongoDB and non-relational database practices so document schemas, queries, indexes, and migrations remain maintainable, performant, and safe in production.

        1. Model documents around access patterns and aggregate boundaries: embed data that is read together, reference data with independent lifecycles, and keep arrays bounded.
        2. Make schemas explicit with validation where practical: document required fields, allowed values, BSON types, indexes, retention rules, and backwards-compatible evolution.
        3. Design queries with stable predicates, projections, sort order, pagination, collation, and parameter validation; avoid unbounded scans and application-side filtering.
        4. Align indexes to real workload shapes: equality prefixes, sort coverage, selectivity, partial filters, unique constraints, TTL retention, and measured lifecycle cleanup.
        5. Build aggregation pipelines that reduce data early, preserve index use, avoid avoidable fan-out, and expose operational limits such as memory, disk use, and stage cost.
        6. Treat consistency, transactions, idempotency, sharding, backups, migrations, and observability as first-class design inputs.

        Do not replace framework skills; complement them with database-level guidance only.
    </goal>

    <constraints>
        <constraints-description>
            Before recommending structural or build changes, ensure the workspace builds. Compilation failure is a blocking condition for Java-side edits.
        </constraints-description>
        <constraint-list>
            <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before changing Java or build descriptors alongside database artifacts</constraint>
            <constraint>**SCOPE**: Stay within MongoDB/non-relational modeling, query, index, migration, and operational guidance; defer framework wiring to 315/415/515 and Mongock migrations to 316/416/516</constraint>
            <constraint>**QUERY SAFETY**: Never build queries, aggregation stages, JSON documents, JavaScript expressions, or `$where` clauses by concatenating untrusted input</constraint>
            <constraint>**EVIDENCE**: Use `explain()` output, index definitions, representative data volume, and query frequency before making performance claims</constraint>
            <constraint>**MAINTAINER**: If you are changing skill source files in a skills-generator repository, regenerate the local skill outputs using the repository's documented build workflow, then run the relevant verification (tests/build) for the changed area</constraint>
        </constraint-list>
    </constraints>

    <examples>
        <toc auto-generate="true" />

        <example number="1" id="document-modeling">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Model documents around access patterns</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>bounded embedded data, independent references, explicit lifecycle</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Embed data that is usually read and updated with the aggregate. Reference data that has an independent lifecycle, high cardinality, or unbounded growth. Call out the expected query shape before choosing either option.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="json"><![CDATA[{
  "_id": "order-1001",
  "customerId": "customer-42",
  "status": "PAID",
  "placedAt": "2026-06-04T10:15:30Z",
  "shippingAddress": {
    "country": "ES",
    "city": "Madrid",
    "postalCode": "28001"
  },
  "lineItems": [
    {
      "sku": "book-123",
      "quantity": 2,
      "unitPrice": "19.95"
    }
  ]
}]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="json"><![CDATA[{
  "_id": "customer-42",
  "orders": [
    { "orderId": "order-1001", "lineItems": [/* grows forever */] },
    { "orderId": "order-1002", "lineItems": [/* grows forever */] }
  ]
}]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="2" id="schema-validation">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Use JSON Schema validation for important contracts</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>required fields, BSON types, enums, and compatibility-aware evolution</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                MongoDB collections can stay flexible while still protecting critical invariants. Use validation for required identifiers, state fields, timestamps, and values that downstream code assumes.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.createCollection("orders", {
  validator: {
    $jsonSchema: {
      bsonType: "object",
      required: ["customerId", "status", "placedAt", "lineItems"],
      properties: {
        customerId: { bsonType: "string" },
        status: { enum: ["PENDING", "PAID", "CANCELLED"] },
        placedAt: { bsonType: "date" },
        lineItems: {
          bsonType: "array",
          minItems: 1,
          items: {
            bsonType: "object",
            required: ["sku", "quantity"],
            properties: {
              sku: { bsonType: "string" },
              quantity: { bsonType: "int", minimum: 1 }
            }
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }
})]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.createCollection("orders")
// No validation for fields that application code treats as mandatory.
// Invalid status values and missing line items can drift into production.]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="3" id="query-and-index-alignment">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Align compound indexes with query shape</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>equality predicates before range and sort fields</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Indexes should match frequent filters and sorts. Check plans with representative data and remove unused indexes after measuring production usage.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.orders.createIndex({ customerId: 1, status: 1, placedAt: -1 })

db.orders.find(
  {
    customerId: "customer-42",
    status: "PAID",
    placedAt: { $gte: ISODate("2026-01-01T00:00:00Z") }
  },
  { _id: 1, status: 1, placedAt: 1, total: 1 }
).sort({ placedAt: -1 }).limit(50).explain("executionStats")]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.orders.find({ status: "PAID" }).toArray()
  .filter(order => order.customerId === "customer-42")
  .sort((left, right) => right.placedAt - left.placedAt)
// Avoid application-side filtering/sorting after an unbounded collection scan.]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="4" id="aggregation-pipeline">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Reduce data early in aggregation pipelines</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>push filters forward, project only needed fields, control fan-out</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Place selective `$match` stages early, project only fields needed downstream, and be deliberate with `$lookup` and `$unwind` because they can multiply intermediate result size.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.orders.aggregate([
  {
    $match: {
      status: "PAID",
      placedAt: { $gte: ISODate("2026-01-01T00:00:00Z") }
    }
  },
  { $project: { customerId: 1, total: 1, placedAt: 1 } },
  { $group: { _id: "$customerId", revenue: { $sum: "$total" } } },
  { $sort: { revenue: -1 } },
  { $limit: 20 }
], { allowDiskUse: true })]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="javascript"><![CDATA[db.orders.aggregate([
  { $lookup: { from: "customers", localField: "customerId", foreignField: "_id", as: "customer" } },
  { $unwind: "$lineItems" },
  { $match: { status: "PAID" } }
])
// Avoid expensive joins and fan-out before selective filters.]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>
    </examples>

    <output-format>
        <output-format-list>
            <output-format-item>**IDENTIFY** workload context: read/write paths, cardinality, retention, consistency requirements, data volume, and operational constraints</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**REVIEW** document schemas for aggregate boundaries, bounded growth, validation, lifecycle ownership, and backwards-compatible evolution</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**ANALYZE** queries and aggregation pipelines for predicate selectivity, projection, sort coverage, pagination, collation, and fan-out risk</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**PROPOSE** concrete collection, index, validation, query, and pipeline snippets that match the stated workload</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**CALL OUT** data migration, zero-downtime rollout, rollback, backup, and retention risks before destructive or incompatible changes</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**DELEGATE** framework-specific repository, client, transaction, and test wiring to the matching Spring Boot, Quarkus, or Micronaut MongoDB skill</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**VALIDATE** changes with build checks, representative tests, schema validation, index inspection, and `explain()` evidence when available</output-format-item>
        </output-format-list>
    </output-format>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>**DATA SAFETY**: Back up data and define rollback steps before destructive schema, index, retention, or migration changes</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**BOUNDED GROWTH**: Avoid unbounded arrays and oversized documents; model high-cardinality children as separate documents when lifecycle or growth requires it</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**QUERY SAFETY**: Validate user-controlled filters, sort fields, projection fields, and pagination limits before constructing database queries</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**PERFORMANCE EVIDENCE**: Prefer measured plans and production-like data over intuition when changing indexes or aggregation pipelines</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**CONSISTENCY**: Document read concern, write concern, transaction boundaries, and idempotency strategy when correctness depends on them</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</prompt>
