<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../skills.xsd"
      id="002-agents-inventory">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to generate a checklist document with embedded agents inventory, following the embedded template exactly and producing INVENTORY-AGENTS-JAVA.md in the project root. This should trigger for requests such as Create embedded agents inventory checklist; Generate INVENTORY-AGENTS-JAVA.md; Use @002-agents-inventory; Inventory embedded Java agent definitions; List generated agent roles for Java development.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Create a Checklist with embedded agents inventory for Java</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Create a comprehensive checklist document for embedded agents inventory by following the embedded template exactly.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Exact-template checklist generation
- Output file creation as `INVENTORY-AGENTS-JAVA.md`
- Strict adherence to listed sections and content
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Follow the template exactly without adding or removing sections, rows, or details.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**DO NOT** create additional rows beyond what the template defines</constraint>
      <constraint>**DO NOT** add agent entries not explicitly listed in the template</constraint>
      <constraint>**ONLY** use exact wording and structure from the embedded template</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If the user goal is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before editing files or running project-wide commands</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required context, files, credentials, or tools are missing, report the blocker explicitly and ask whether to proceed with setup or fallback guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If requested changes conflict with project constraints or safety boundaries, explain the conflict and ask for user confirmation on the preferred trade-off</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>Create embedded agents inventory checklist</trigger>
      <trigger>Generate INVENTORY-AGENTS-JAVA.md</trigger>
      <trigger>Use @002-agents-inventory</trigger>
        <trigger>Inventory embedded Java agent definitions</trigger>
        <trigger>List generated agent roles for Java development</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read the embedded template</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/002-agents-inventory.md` before generating output and use it as the authoritative template.</step-content>
      <step-constraints>
        <step-constraint-list>
          <step-constraint>Do not use cached or partial template content</step-constraint>
          <step-constraint>Preserve exact table rows, headings, and structure from the reference</step-constraint>
        </step-constraint-list>
      </step-constraints>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Generate inventory document</step-title>
      <step-content>Create `INVENTORY-AGENTS-JAVA.md` in the project root using the exact wording and ordering from the reference template.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Validate template fidelity</step-title>
      <step-content>Confirm no extra agent rows were introduced and all required reference sections are present in the generated file.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
