<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="025-quality-attribute-discovery"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when a problem under exploration needs its quality attributes (non-functional requirements) identified and prioritized before architecture and design begin. This should trigger when an issue's Quality Attribute Discovery point of view needs evaluation, or when a maintainer directly asks to discover and prioritize candidate quality attributes for a problem, before any ADR or design work starts.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Quality Attribute Discovery</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Guide identification and prioritization of the quality attributes a future solution must satisfy, before architecture and design decisions begin. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Identifying candidate quality attributes (for example performance, security, availability, maintainability, scalability, usability, observability) relevant to the problem
- Grounding each candidate in evidence from the problem frame, root causes, assumptions, and context map, not a generic checklist
- Prioritizing candidate quality attributes by stakeholder impact and risk
- Stopping at a prioritized discovery list rather than selecting or recording an architectural decision
- Explicitly not producing ADRs or an architecture direction itself
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Discover and prioritize candidate quality attributes as input to later architecture work; do not make or record the architecture decision here. When this technique is orchestrated by another workflow, the orchestrator owns clarifying-question sequencing; when applied standalone, ask directly.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MUST** read `references/025-quality-attribute-discovery.md` before applying Quality Attribute Discovery guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** ground each candidate quality attribute in evidence from the problem frame, root causes, assumptions, or context map</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** prioritize candidate quality attributes by stakeholder impact and risk, not list them unordered</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** stop at a prioritized discovery list without selecting or recording an architecture decision</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST NOT** record an architectural decision, ADR, or design direction as part of this skill's output</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST NOT** invent a quality attribute or priority when the available content is vague or ambiguous; flag the gap for a clarifying question instead</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>Discover the quality attributes for this problem</trigger>
      <trigger>Identify non-functional requirements before design begins</trigger>
      <trigger>Prioritize candidate quality attributes for this issue</trigger>
      <trigger>Apply quality attribute discovery before architecture decisions</trigger>
      <trigger>Draft the Quality Attribute Discovery section of a Functional Specification</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read the Reference</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/025-quality-attribute-discovery.md`, then review the problem frame, root-cause findings, assumptions, and context map for evidence of quality pressure.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Identify Candidate Quality Attributes</step-title>
      <step-content>Identify candidate quality attributes grounded in that evidence, avoiding a generic unfiltered checklist.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Prioritize by Impact and Risk</step-title>
      <step-content>Prioritize the candidate quality attributes by stakeholder impact and risk if unmet.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Stop Before Architecture Decisions</step-title>
      <step-content>Stop at the prioritized discovery list; do not select an architecture approach or record an ADR here.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Report the Discovery List</step-title>
      <step-content>Report the prioritized quality attributes, stating explicitly that the output stops at this discovery list and does not select or record an architecture decision; flag any item left open pending a clarifying answer.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
