<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../skills.xsd"
      id="033-architecture-diagrams"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to generate Java project diagrams — including UML sequence diagrams, UML class diagrams, C4 model diagrams, UML state machine diagrams, UML Deployment Diagrams, ER (Entity Relationship) diagrams, and bounded-context diagrams — through a modular, step-based interactive process that adapts to your specific visualization needs. This should trigger for requests such as Generate UML diagram; Create sequence diagram; Create class diagram; Create state machine diagram; Create deployment diagram; Create C4 diagram; Create bounded-context diagram; Create context-map diagram.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java Diagrams Generator with modular step-based configuration</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Generate comprehensive Java project diagrams through a modular, step-based interactive process that covers UML sequence diagrams, UML class diagrams, C4 model diagrams, UML state machine diagrams, UML Deployment Diagrams, ER (Entity Relationship) diagrams, and bounded-context diagrams using PlantUML syntax. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- UML sequence diagram generation for application workflows and API interactions
- UML class diagram generation for package structure and class relationships
- C4 model diagram generation for Context, Container, and Component diagrams
- UML state machine diagram generation for entity lifecycles and business workflows
- UML Deployment Diagram generation for runtime topology, nodes, execution environments, deployed components, data stores, queues, external systems, and communication paths
- ER diagram generation from SQL schema (DDL, migrations) using PlantUML Chen notation
- Bounded-context diagram generation for DDD context maps across one or more repositories
- PlantUML syntax for all diagram types
- File organization strategies: single-file, separate-files, or integrated with existing documentation
- Final diagram validation with PlantUML syntax checking
- PlantUML validation and PNG/SVG rendering with a trusted local PlantUML installation or repository-approved wrapper
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Before applying any diagram generation, ensure the project validates. If validation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until all validation errors are resolved.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw validate` or `mvn validate` before applying any diagram generation</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If validation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until all validation errors are resolved</constraint>
      <constraint><![CDATA[**BEFORE READING DIAGRAM REFERENCES**: Run the question flow embedded in this SKILL.md first. Ask the diagram preference questions one by one, collect selected diagram families and output preferences, then read only the implementation references selected by the user's answers]]></constraint>
      <constraint>**C4 SCOPE**: C4 diagrams are restricted to Context, Container, and Component diagrams</constraint>
      <constraint>**SUPPLY CHAIN**: Generated PlantUML diagrams must use trusted local includes only; do not use remote `!include` URLs for C4 or icon libraries</constraint>
      <constraint>**TOOLING SAFETY**: Use only trusted local PlantUML tooling or a repository-approved wrapper; do not pull or run remote container images as part of this skill</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Generate UML diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create sequence diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create class diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create state machine diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create deployment diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create C4 diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Generate ER diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create bounded-context diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create context-map diagram</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Validate project state</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `./mvnw validate` or `mvn validate` before applying any diagram generation.</step-content>
      <step-constraints>
        <step-constraint-list>
          <step-constraint>If validation fails, stop and ask to resolve errors first</step-constraint>
        </step-constraint-list>
      </step-constraints>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Ask diagram assessment questions before reading references</step-title>
      <step-content><![CDATA[
Run this XML-included question flow before reading any diagram-family implementation reference. Ask questions one-by-one in strict order, wait for the user's answer to each question, and record selected diagram families, C4 scope, bounded-context repository scope, output organization, file format, and documentation preference before continuing.

]]><xi:include href="../skill-references/assets/questions/033-architecture-diagrams-questions.xml"/><![CDATA[

After all applicable questions are answered, confirm the selections and map them to references:

- If UML sequence diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-uml-sequence.md`.
- If UML class diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-uml-class.md`.
- If C4 model diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-c4.md`.
- If UML state-machine diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-state-machine.md`.
- If UML Deployment Diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-deployment.md`.
- If ER diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-er.md`.
- If bounded-context diagrams are selected, read `references/033-architecture-diagrams-bounded-context.md`.
- If All diagrams is selected, read all seven focused diagram-family references.
- If Skip is selected for a diagram family, do not read that diagram-family reference.
- Do not read unselected diagram-family references.
]]></step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Read selected references and generate PlantUML diagrams</step-title>
      <step-content>Create requested diagrams in PlantUML syntax using only the selected focused references, project inputs, and repository context.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Validate and finalize outputs</step-title>
      <step-content><![CDATA[
Check generated diagrams for syntax correctness and consistency with selected scope before final delivery.

Use an already installed PlantUML CLI or a repository-approved wrapper to validate and render generated `.puml` files. If PlantUML is not available, report the missing trusted tool and provide setup guidance instead of downloading or running remote execution artifacts.

Validate PlantUML syntax without generating images:

```bash
plantuml -checkonly diagrams
```

Render PNG images:

```bash
plantuml -tpng diagrams
```

Render SVG images:

```bash
plantuml -tsvg diagrams
```

Point the command at the directory or `.puml` file containing generated diagrams. Do not pull or run external container images during validation.
]]></step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
