<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="701-technologies-openapi">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need framework-agnostic OpenAPI 3.x guidance — spec structure, metadata and versioning, paths and operations, reusable schemas, security schemes, examples, documentation quality, contract validation (e.g. Spectral), breaking-change awareness, and handoffs to codegen — without choosing Spring Boot, Quarkus, or Micronaut. This should trigger for requests such as Review an OpenAPI; Improve an OpenAPI; Improve API contract; Improve API schema design.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>OpenAPI 3.x best practices</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Help teams produce maintainable **OpenAPI 3.x** contracts that stay aligned with HTTP semantics and consumer needs.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Document structure: `openapi`, `info`, `servers`, `tags`, and consistent resource grouping
- Path and operation design: parameters, request bodies, response matrices, `operationId`, status codes
- Reusable `components` (schemas, parameters, responses, security schemes) and examples
- Validation and CI: spec linting, breaking-change checks, pre-codegen gates
- Security modeling in the contract (schemes, scopes, global vs operation security)
- Clear boundaries between contract-first design and runtime implementation concerns

**Scope:** Contract-first quality only. Focus this skill on OpenAPI design, quality, and governance guidance.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Keep recommendations at the OpenAPI layer unless the user explicitly asks for Java framework integration. After editing this repository's XML sources, regenerate skills and verify the build.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before proposing Java or Maven changes in the same change set</constraint>
      <constraint>**FRAMEWORK**: Keep guidance contract-centric; do not prescribe framework-specific controller wiring or runtime exposure details</constraint>
      <constraint>**FUZZING**: Keep fuzzing guidance high-level and contract-focused without linking to external skill identifiers</constraint>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Regenerate skills with `./mvnw clean install -pl plinth-skills-generator` after editing skill or system-prompt XML in this repo</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` before promoting changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If the user goal is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before editing files or running project-wide commands</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required context, files, credentials, or tools are missing, report the blocker explicitly and ask whether to proceed with setup or fallback guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If requested changes conflict with project constraints or safety boundaries, explain the conflict and ask for user confirmation on the preferred trade-off</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Review an OpenAPI</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve an OpenAPI</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve API contract</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve API schema design</trigger>
        <trigger>Validate an OpenAPI spec</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>
  <steps>
    <step number="1"><step-title>Read reference and assess project context</step-title><step-content>Read `references/701-technologies-openapi.md` and inspect current API/context artifacts before proposing changes.</step-content></step>
    <step number="2"><step-title>Gather scope and decide target improvements</step-title><step-content>Identify requested outcomes, constraints, and the minimum safe set of changes to apply.</step-content></step>
    <step number="3"><step-title>Apply technology-aligned changes</step-title><step-content>Implement or refactor artifacts following the reference patterns and project conventions.</step-content></step>
    <step number="4"><step-title>Run verification and report results</step-title><step-content>Execute appropriate checks and summarize what changed, what was verified, and any follow-up actions.</step-content></step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
