<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="030-architecture-adr-general"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.16.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to generate Architecture Decision Records (ADRs) for a Java project through an interactive, conversational process that systematically gathers context, stakeholders, options, and outcomes to produce well-structured ADR documents. This should trigger for requests such as Generate ADR; Create Architecture Decision Record; Document architecture decision; Architecture Decision Record for Java.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java ADR Generator with interactive conversational approach</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Generate Architecture Decision Records (ADRs) for Java projects through an interactive, conversational process that elicits the decision inputs needed for a well-structured ADR. **This is an interactive SKILL**. Use only the current conversation and repository files explicitly available in the current session; do not expose, persist, or reuse unrelated user/project context.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- ADR file storage configuration
- Conversational information gathering: context, stakeholders, decision drivers, options with pros/cons, outcome, consequences
- MADR template generation
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Handle ambiguity and blockers explicitly to avoid implicit assumptions.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If the user goal is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before editing files or running project-wide commands</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required context, files, credentials, or tools are missing, report the blocker explicitly and ask whether to proceed with setup or fallback guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If requested changes conflict with project constraints or safety boundaries, explain the conflict and ask for user confirmation on the preferred trade-off</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Generate ADR</trigger>
        <trigger>Create Architecture Decision Record</trigger>
        <trigger>Document architecture decision</trigger>
        <trigger>Architecture Decision Record for Java</trigger>
        <trigger>Write ADR</trigger>
        <trigger>Document technical decision</trigger>
        <trigger>Architecture documentation</trigger>
        <trigger>Record design decision</trigger>
        <trigger>Technology choice documentation</trigger>
        <trigger>Framework selection ADR</trigger>
        <trigger>Database choice ADR</trigger>
        <trigger>Architectural trade-offs</trigger>
        <trigger>Technical alternatives evaluation</trigger>
        <trigger>Why did we choose</trigger>
        <trigger>Deployment strategy ADR</trigger>
        <trigger>Infrastructure choice</trigger>
        <trigger>Vendor selection ADR</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Load ADR reference and elicit decision inputs</step-title>
      <step-content>Load `references/030-architecture-adr-general.md` from this skill, then elicit stakeholders, decision drivers, options, and trade-offs through the current conversation only.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Synthesize and confirm decision</step-title>
      <step-content>Summarize recommended option, rationale, and consequences, and confirm alignment with the user before creating the ADR artifact.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Generate ADR output</step-title>
      <step-content>Create a MADR-style ADR document with the final decision, alternatives, consequences, and follow-up actions.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
