<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="032-architecture-adr-non-functional-requirements"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.15.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Facilitates conversational discovery to create Architectural Decision Records (ADRs) for non-functional requirements using the ISO/IEC 25010:2023 quality model. Use when the user wants to document quality attributes, NFR decisions, security/performance/scalability architecture, or design systems with measurable quality criteria. This should trigger for requests such as Create ADR for Non-functional requirements; Document Non-functional requirements; Capture Non-functional requirements; Generate Non-functional requirements in an ADR.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Create ADRs for Non-Functional Requirements</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Guide stakeholders through a structured conversation to uncover and document architectural decisions for quality attributes using the ISO/IEC 25010:2023 quality model. **This is an interactive SKILL**. The ADR documents the outcome of the conversation, not the conversation itself. Act as an architecture consultant: challenge-first, consultative, adaptive.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Challenge-first opening: ISO 25010:2023 quality characteristics (Functional Suitability, Performance Efficiency, Compatibility, Reliability, Security, Maintainability, Flexibility, Safety)
- Understanding the challenge: drivers, constraints, system context
- Quality-specific deep dive tailored to primary NFR category
- Solution exploration and trade-off preferences
- Decision synthesis and validation before ADR creation
- ADR document generation with Quality Metrics &amp; Success Criteria
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Use challenge-first, consultative discovery—ask 1-2 questions at a time, build on answers, tailor to NFR category. Only create ADR after thorough conversation and user confirmation.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `date` before starting to get accurate timestamps for the ADR</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Read the reference template fresh—do not use cached questions</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Start with challenge-first opening (ISO 25010:2023 quality characteristics)</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Ask one or two questions at a time; never all at once</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Validate summary with user (Does this accurately capture your quality needs?) before proposing ADR creation</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Wait for user to confirm proceed before generating the ADR</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Create ADR for Non-functional requirements</trigger>
        <trigger>Document Non-functional requirements</trigger>
        <trigger>Capture Non-functional requirements</trigger>
        <trigger>Generate Non-functional requirements in an ADR</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="0">
      <step-title>Get current date</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `date` before discovery and use it for ADR timestamps.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read reference and open with quality challenge</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/032-architecture-adr-non-functional-requirements.md` and begin with the challenge-first ISO 25010:2023 quality characteristics framing.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Run consultative NFR discovery</step-title>
      <step-content>Ask one or two questions at a time to capture drivers, constraints, quality priorities, options, and trade-off preferences tailored to the primary NFR category.</step-content>
      <step-constraints>
        <step-constraint-list>
          <step-constraint>Never ask all discovery questions at once</step-constraint>
          <step-constraint>Validate summary with user before proposing ADR generation</step-constraint>
        </step-constraint-list>
      </step-constraints>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Generate ADR after explicit confirmation</step-title>
      <step-content>Only after user confirms proceed, create the ADR including measurable Quality Metrics and Success Criteria.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
