<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="033-architecture-diagrams"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.15.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to generate Java project diagrams — including UML sequence diagrams, UML class diagrams, C4 model diagrams, UML state machine diagrams, and ER (Entity Relationship) diagrams — through a modular, step-based interactive process that adapts to your specific visualization needs.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java Diagrams Generator with modular step-based configuration</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Generate comprehensive Java project diagrams through a modular, step-based interactive process that covers UML sequence diagrams, UML class diagrams, C4 model diagrams, UML state machine diagrams, and ER (Entity Relationship) diagrams using PlantUML syntax. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- UML sequence diagram generation for application workflows and API interactions
- UML class diagram generation for package structure and class relationships
- C4 model diagram generation at Context/Container/Component levels only (levels 1–3; Code/Level 4 not generated)
- UML state machine diagram generation for entity lifecycles and business workflows
- ER diagram generation from SQL schema (DDL, migrations) using PlantUML Chen notation
- PlantUML syntax for all diagram types
- File organization strategies: single-file, separate-files, or integrated with existing documentation
- Final diagram validation with PlantUML syntax checking
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Before applying any diagram generation, ensure the project validates. If validation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until all validation errors are resolved.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw validate` or `mvn validate` before applying any diagram generation</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If validation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until all validation errors are resolved</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed good/bad examples, constraints, and safeguards for each diagram generation pattern</constraint>
      <constraint>**C4 LIMIT**: C4 diagrams restricted to levels 1, 2, 3 only (Context, Container, Component); never generate Level 4 (Code) diagrams</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Generate UML diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create sequence diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create class diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create state machine diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Create C4 diagram</trigger>
        <trigger>Generate ER diagram</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Validate project state</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `./mvnw validate` or `mvn validate` before applying any diagram generation.</step-content>
      <step-constraints>
        <step-constraint-list>
          <step-constraint>If validation fails, stop and ask to resolve errors first</step-constraint>
        </step-constraint-list>
      </step-constraints>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Read reference and configure diagram scope</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/033-architecture-diagrams.md`, identify requested diagram types, and confirm output organization strategy (single-file, separate-files, or integrated docs).</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Generate PlantUML diagrams</step-title>
      <step-content>Create requested diagrams in PlantUML syntax (sequence, class, C4 levels 1-3 only, state machine, ER) using project inputs and context.</step-content>
      <step-constraints>
        <step-constraint-list>
          <step-constraint>Never generate C4 Level 4 (Code) diagrams</step-constraint>
        </step-constraint-list>
      </step-constraints>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Validate and finalize outputs</step-title>
      <step-content>Check generated diagrams for syntax correctness and consistency with selected scope before final delivery.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>

  <references>
    <reference-list>
        <reference>references/033-architecture-diagrams.md</reference>
    </reference-list>
  </references>
</prompt>
