<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="041-planning-plan-mode"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.16.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when creating a plan using Plan model and enhancing structured design plans in Cursor Plan mode for Java implementations. Use when the user wants to create a plan, design an implementation, structure a development plan, or use plan mode for outside-in TDD, feature implementation, or refactoring work. This should trigger for requests such as Create a plan with Cursor Plan mode; Write a plan with Claude Plan mode; Design an implementation plan; Structure a development plan.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java Design Plan Creation for Cursor Plan Mode</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Guide the process of creating a structured plan using Cursor Plan mode. **This is an interactive SKILL**. Plans follow a consistent section structure suitable for Java feature implementation, refactoring, or API design.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Plan mode workflow: enter Plan mode, gather context, draft plan, iterate
- YAML frontmatter: name, overview, todos, isProject
- Required sections: Requirements Summary, Approach (with Mermaid), Task List, Execution Instructions, File Checklist, Notes
- London Style (outside-in) TDD pattern
- Plan execution discipline: update Status after each task before advancing
- Plan storage: ask user for preferred folder and filename convention before creating artifact
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Gather context before drafting. Include Execution Instructions in every plan. Never advance to next task without updating the plan's Status column.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `date` before starting to get date prefix for plan filename</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Read the reference template fresh—do not use cached content</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Ask one or two questions at a time; never all at once</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Validate summary (Does this capture what you need?) before proposing plan creation</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Wait for user to confirm proceed before generating the plan</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Ask the user where they want to store the plan before generating the plan artifact</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Include Execution Instructions section in every generated plan</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Create a plan with Cursor Plan mode</trigger>
        <trigger>Write a plan with Claude Plan mode</trigger>
        <trigger>Design an implementation plan</trigger>
        <trigger>Structure a development plan</trigger>
        <trigger>Create a structured design plan</trigger>
        <trigger>Refactor the plan</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve the plan</trigger>
        <trigger>Update the plan</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="0">
      <step-title>Get current date</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `date` before planning and use it to derive the plan filename prefix `YYYY-MM-DD`.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read reference and gather context</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/041-planning-plan-mode.md` and ask one or two questions at a time to clarify requirements, constraints, and target scope.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Validate summary and confirm proceed</step-title>
      <step-content>Summarize understanding, ask Does this capture what you need?, and wait for explicit proceed before creating the plan artifact.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Confirm plan storage location</step-title>
      <step-content>Ask where the user wants to store the plan (for example, `.cursor/plans/` or another folder) and confirm the target filename pattern before writing.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Generate structured plan artifact</step-title>
      <step-content>Create the plan at the confirmed location using required sections and YAML frontmatter, including Execution Instructions.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Apply execution discipline</step-title>
      <step-content>When executing tasks from the plan, update the Status column after each task before moving to the next one.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
