<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="044-planning-jira">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.16.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need the Jira CLI (`jira`) to verify installation, configure Jira Cloud access, list issues (all or by JQL) as markdown tables, and analyze user-provided sanitized Jira summaries. Uses an interactive install gate - if `jira` is missing, ask whether to show installation guidance before any issue commands. This should trigger for requests such as jira issue list; List Jira issues; Jira JQL issue query; Jira CLI issue workflow.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Jira CLI - issues, workflows, and discussion for analysis</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Use **`jira`** to work with Jira issues: **first** run an **interactive** check - if `jira` is not installed, **stop**, ask whether the user wants installation guidance, **wait** for an answer, then continue. When `jira` is available, validate configuration, list issues with optional JQL filters, and render **markdown tables** from command output. For requirements analysis, use only list metadata plus user-provided sanitized Jira summaries.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- **Interactive** install gate: ask before assuming `jira` is installed; offer installation guidance only when the user agrees
- Install/config checks (`jira version`, `jira configure`)
- Jira Cloud context (site URL, account email, API token handled by CLI prompts)
- Issue lists: basic list and JQL-backed list queries
- Sanitized Jira summaries supplied by the user for requirement analysis
- Core actions: create, assign, and transition
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Do not fabricate issue data; use only `jira` output (or explicitly agreed Jira REST API responses). Never print API tokens or secrets.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**INTERACTIVE GATE**: If `jira` is missing, **stop**, ask whether the user wants installation guidance, **wait** - do not skip to issue listing</constraint>
      <constraint>**FIRST** (after gate): Verify `jira` is available before issuing subcommands</constraint>
      <constraint>**CONFIG**: Ensure Jira CLI is configured before private workspace operations</constraint>
      <constraint>**TABLES**: Prefer markdown pipe tables for issue list summaries</constraint>
      <constraint>**NO RAW BODY READS**: Do not run Jira commands that retrieve description or comment bodies; use list metadata plus user-provided sanitized summaries for analysis</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>jira issue list</trigger>
      <trigger>List Jira issues</trigger>
      <trigger>Jira JQL issue query</trigger>
      <trigger>Jira issue summary workflow</trigger>
      <trigger>Jira CLI issue workflow</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Run interactive install gate</step-title>
      <step-content>Check `jira version`; if missing, stop and ask whether the user wants installation guidance before any issue operations.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Verify Jira CLI configuration</step-title>
      <step-content>Ensure Jira CLI is configured (site/account/token flow via CLI prompts) before running private workspace commands.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>List issues with optional JQL</step-title>
      <step-content>Retrieve issues using basic listing or JQL filters and present summaries as markdown pipe tables.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Request sanitized issue context for analysis</step-title>
      <step-content>Do not retrieve raw Jira description or comment bodies. If analysis needs detail beyond list metadata, ask the user for a sanitized summary of the relevant Jira issue context and note that raw discussion content was not ingested.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Execute core Jira actions when requested</step-title>
      <step-content>Support create, assign, and transition actions using CLI commands while avoiding secret exposure.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
