<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="051-design-two-steps-methods"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.17.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when a complex or risky code change should be split into Kent Beck's two-step method by first making the change easy through behavior-preserving preparatory refactoring, then making the intended behavior change once the design supports it. This should trigger for requests such as Apply two-step change; Make this risky change safer; Refactor before changing behavior; Separate preparation from behavior change.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Two-Step Change Method</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Guide Java developers through complex or risky changes by keeping design preparation separate from behavior modification. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Clarifying the intended behavior change before editing
- Identifying design obstacles that make the change difficult or risky
- Step 1: behavior-preserving preparatory refactoring that makes the change easy
- Validation that Step 1 preserves existing behavior
- Step 2: the smallest intended behavior change after the design supports it
- Verification that Step 2 delivers the intended behavior
- Handoff to focused Java, framework, persistence, messaging, API, or testing skills while preserving the two-step sequence
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Separate behavior-preserving preparation from behavior-changing work, and validate after each step.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MUST**: State the intended behavior change before proposing preparatory refactoring</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Keep Step 1 behavior-preserving; do not mix broad refactoring with the intended behavior change</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Verify existing behavior after Step 1 using the project-appropriate tests, build, characterization tests, or manual checks</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Make Step 2 only after the design has been prepared and validated</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Verify the intended behavior after Step 2 with focused tests and relevant build checks</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST**: Record assumptions and risks when preparation cannot be fully separated from behavior change</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>Apply two-step change</trigger>
      <trigger>Make this risky change safer</trigger>
      <trigger>Refactor before changing behavior</trigger>
      <trigger>Separate preparation from behavior change</trigger>
      <trigger>Make the change easy, then make the easy change</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Define the intended change</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/051-design-two-steps-methods.md`, inspect the relevant code and tests, and state the exact behavior or capability that must change. Identify why the current design makes the change complex, risky, or hard to verify.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Plan preparatory refactoring</step-title>
      <step-content>Choose the smallest behavior-preserving refactoring that reduces the obstacle: extract method or class, clarify names, isolate dependencies, add seams for testing, move responsibilities, improve types, or add characterization tests before touching behavior.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Make the change easy</step-title>
      <step-content>Apply Step 1 as focused preparatory refactoring only. Keep commits, notes, or task boundaries clear enough that reviewers can see no intended behavior change is included.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Validate preserved behavior</step-title>
      <step-content>Run the relevant existing tests, build checks, characterization tests, or manual verification. If behavior changes unexpectedly, fix or revert the preparation before proceeding.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Make the easy behavior change</step-title>
      <step-content>Apply the smallest intended behavior change now that the design supports it. Use focused Java, framework, persistence, messaging, API, or testing skills when detailed implementation guidance is needed.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="6">
      <step-title>Verify and report the outcome</step-title>
      <step-content>Verify the intended behavior with targeted tests and relevant project validation. Report what was preparation, what changed behavior, what was verified after each step, and any remaining risks.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
