<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="055-design-parallel-change"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.17.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when a database schema or data-meaning change needs Parallel Change, including expand, migrate, and contract sequencing for column renames, type or data reinterpretation, large-table backfills, relationship-table changes, enum/status transitions, timezone/default changes, and index or uniqueness changes. This should trigger before framework-specific Flyway implementation guidance when deciding whether a migration needs a compatibility window or whether a simpler migration is sufficient.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Parallel Change Design</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Guide Java Enterprise developers through Parallel Change for database migration scenarios. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Deciding whether a database migration needs a compatibility window
- Sequencing database changes as expand, migrate, and contract deployable steps
- Preserving old and new application versions during rollout and rollback windows
- Handling column renames, type or data reinterpretation, large backfills, relationship-table changes, and index or uniqueness changes
- Explaining tradeoffs such as temporary dual paths, extra migrations, verification effort, and delayed cleanup
- Routing framework-specific implementation to Spring Boot, Quarkus, or Micronaut Flyway skills after the design approach is clear
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Use Parallel Change as a database migration design pattern, then hand off implementation details to the framework-specific migration skill when needed.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MUST** read `references/055-design-parallel-change.md` before applying Parallel Change guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** explain expand, migrate, and contract as separate deployable steps when recommending Parallel Change</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** decide whether Parallel Change is needed before recommending framework-specific Flyway implementation details</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** recommend a simpler single migration when the change is additive, immediately safe, and does not require old and new application versions to coexist</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** describe the compatibility, data-preservation, verification, and cleanup tradeoffs of the chosen approach</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** use framework-specific Flyway skills for Spring Boot, Quarkus, or Micronaut implementation details after the migration strategy is selected</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>Apply Parallel Change to this database migration</trigger>
      <trigger>Use expand migrate contract for this schema change</trigger>
      <trigger>Plan a safe column rename migration</trigger>
      <trigger>Plan a zero-downtime database migration</trigger>
      <trigger>Should this Flyway migration use Parallel Change?</trigger>
      <trigger>Design a safe backfill and contract migration</trigger>
      <trigger>Decide if this schema change needs a compatibility window</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Classify the Migration Risk</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/055-design-parallel-change.md`, then identify the schema shape, data meaning, application read/write path, rollout window, rollback expectation, and production-data risk affected by the migration.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Choose Parallel Change or Simpler Migration</step-title>
      <step-content>Recommend Parallel Change when old and new application versions or data interpretations must coexist. Recommend a simpler forward-only migration when the change is additive, small, immediately safe, and does not require a compatibility window.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Design Expand, Migrate, Contract</step-title>
      <step-content>For Parallel Change, separate expand, migrate, and contract into independently deployable steps. Keep the old shape valid during expand and migrate; contract only after all deployed code and data have moved to the new shape.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Plan Verification and Operations</step-title>
      <step-content>Define previous-release fixture checks, row-count expectations, duplicate detection, backfill monitoring, rollback behavior, and cleanup ownership. Prefer production-dialect migration tests and production-like data samples where feasible.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Route Framework Implementation</step-title>
      <step-content>After the strategy is clear, use `313-frameworks-spring-db-migrations-flyway`, `413-frameworks-quarkus-db-migrations-flyway`, or `513-frameworks-micronaut-db-migrations-flyway` for framework-specific Flyway dependencies, configuration, migration locations, and tests.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="6">
      <step-title>Report the Migration Plan</step-title>
      <step-content>Report the chosen approach, rejected alternative, expand/migrate/contract sequence or simpler migration, verification evidence, cleanup trigger, tradeoffs, skipped checks, and remaining risks.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
