<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="056-design-avoid-breaking-changes"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to review a plan, OpenSpec change, specification, or implementation proposal for breaking-change risk across commands, skills, generated outputs, XML sources, README/docs, tests, CI, APIs, schemas, configuration, data, migration, and release guidance. This should trigger for requests such as Review breaking changes in this spec; Check compatibility risks; Avoid breaking changes in this OpenSpec change; Review migration impact before release; Assess command and skill compatibility.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Avoid Breaking Changes</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Review planned repository changes for breaking-change and compatibility risk before implementation or release promotion. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Command contract compatibility: names, inputs, owning agents, outputs, safeguards, installer registration, and command inventories
- Skill routing compatibility: identifiers, metadata, descriptions, triggers, references, generated local output, and acceptance coverage
- Generated-output ownership: XML/source files versus `.agents/skills`, public `skills/`, `.cursor/commands`, `.cursor/rules`, and `docs/`
- Source and generator contracts: XML, XInclude, XSLT, Maven modules, schema expectations, and module validation
- README, localized README, changelog, migration, and deprecation guidance
- External and runtime contracts: APIs, schemas, data formats, configuration keys, persistence, CLI behavior, and CI expectations
- Structured compatibility reports with severity-ranked findings and validation guidance
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Keep the review evidence-based, read-only, and scoped to compatibility risk unless the user explicitly asks for implementation.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MUST** read `references/056-design-avoid-breaking-changes.md` before producing compatibility guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** identify the source artifacts reviewed and the compatibility surfaces considered</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** distinguish confirmed breaking changes, potential risks, non-breaking changes, and unknowns that need maintainer decision</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** include migration, deprecation, validation, or release-note guidance for intentional breaking changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST** respect repository source ownership: edit XML and source docs, regenerate generated output through documented workflows, and avoid direct generated-output edits unless the repository explicitly owns that file</constraint>
      <constraint>**MUST NOT** modify plans, specs, source files, generated outputs, or issue descriptions during review unless the user explicitly requests implementation</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
      <trigger>Review breaking changes in this spec</trigger>
      <trigger>Check compatibility risks</trigger>
      <trigger>Avoid breaking changes in this OpenSpec change</trigger>
      <trigger>Review migration impact before release</trigger>
      <trigger>Assess command and skill compatibility</trigger>
      <trigger>Find generated output compatibility risks</trigger>
      <trigger>Review API schema configuration or data contract changes</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read the compatibility reference</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/056-design-avoid-breaking-changes.md`, then identify the source artifacts to review, their authority, and whether the request is read-only review or approved implementation.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Inventory compatibility surfaces</step-title>
      <step-content>Check commands, skills, generated outputs, XML/source ownership, README/docs, tests, CI/build gates, external contracts, runtime behavior, data/configuration contracts, and release or migration guidance relevant to the proposed change.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Classify findings</step-title>
      <step-content>Classify each finding as `BREAKING`, `POTENTIALLY BREAKING`, `NON-BREAKING`, or `UNKNOWN`. Include the affected users, artifacts, contracts, and validation evidence or missing evidence.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Recommend migration and validation</step-title>
      <step-content>For each confirmed or potential risk, recommend deprecation, compatibility windows, migration notes, release-note updates, generator checks, focused tests, or owner decisions.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="5">
      <step-title>Report the review outcome</step-title>
      <step-content>Produce a concise compatibility report with reviewed sources, risk summary by surface, severity-ranked findings, recommended validation, and a clear no-risk statement when no breaking-change risks are found.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
