<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="126-java-exception-handling">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.17.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to apply Java exception handling best practices — including using specific exception types, managing resources with try-with-resources, securing exception messages, preserving error context via exception chaining, validating inputs early with fail-fast principles, handling thread interruption correctly, documenting exceptions with @throws, enforcing logging policy, translating exceptions at API boundaries, managing retries and idempotency, enforcing timeouts, attaching suppressed exceptions, and propagating failures in async/reactive code. This should trigger for requests such as Exception handling; Use try-with-resources in Java code; Create exception chaining in Java code; Apply fail-fast validation in Java code; Review Java exception taxonomy and propagation.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java Exception Handling Guidelines</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Identify and apply robust Java exception handling practices to improve error clarity, security, debuggability, and system reliability.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Specific exception types instead of generic `Exception`/`RuntimeException`
- try-with-resources for automatic resource cleanup
- Secure exception messages that avoid information leakage
- Exception chaining to preserve full error context
- Early input validation with `IllegalArgumentException`/`NullPointerException`
- `InterruptedException` handling with interrupted-status restoration
- `@throws` JavaDoc documentation, fail-fast principle
- Structured logging with correlation IDs, avoiding log-and-throw duplication
- API boundary translation via centralized exception mappers
- Bounded retry with backoff for idempotent operations only
- Timeout enforcement with deadline propagation
- `Throwable#addSuppressed` for secondary cleanup failures
- Never catching `Throwable`/`Error`
- Observability via error metrics
- Failure propagation in async `CompletionStage` code

**Scope:** The reference is organized by examples (good/bad code patterns) for each core area. Apply recommendations based on applicable examples.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Before applying any exception handling changes, ensure the project compiles. If compilation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until resolved. After applying improvements, run full verification.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before applying any changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If compilation fails, stop immediately — do not proceed until the project is in a valid state</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed good/bad examples, constraints, and safeguards for each exception handling pattern</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Exception handling</trigger>
        <trigger>Use try-with-resources in Java code</trigger>
        <trigger>Create exception chaining in Java code</trigger>
        <trigger>Apply fail-fast validation in Java code</trigger>
        <trigger>Review Java exception taxonomy and propagation</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Compile project before exception-handling changes</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` and stop immediately if compilation fails.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Read exception-handling reference</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/126-java-exception-handling.md` and identify applicable failure-handling and observability improvements.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Apply exception-handling improvements</step-title>
      <step-content>Refactor to specific exceptions, safe resource handling, error translation, and consistent logging patterns.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Verify with full build</step-title>
      <step-content>Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
