<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="151-java-performance-jmeter">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.17.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to set up JMeter performance testing for a Java project — including creating the run-jmeter.sh script from the exact template, configuring load tests with loops, threads, and ramp-up, or running performance tests from the project root with custom or default settings. This should trigger for requests such as Improve the code with JMeter performance testing; Apply JMeter performance testing; Refactor the code with JMeter performance testing; Add JMeter support; Create a JMeter test plan for a Java service.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Run performance tests based on JMeter</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Provide a complete JMeter performance testing solution by creating the run-jmeter.sh script from the exact template, making it executable, and configuring the project structure for load testing. Supports custom loops, threads, ramp-up, and environment variable overrides.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Create run-jmeter.sh in project root from the exact template (no modifications)
- Project structure: src/test/resources/jmeter/load-test.jmx, target/ for results
- Script options: -l (loops), -t (threads), -r (ramp-up), -g (GUI), -h (help)
- Environment variables: JMETER_LOOPS, JMETER_THREADS, JMETER_RAMP_UP
- Verify JMeter is installed and available before proceeding

**Scope:** Copy the script template verbatim. Do not modify, interpret, or enhance the template content.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>JMeter must be installed and available in PATH. If not available, show a message and exit. Use only the exact template for the run-jmeter.sh script.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**PREREQUISITE**: Verify JMeter is installed and accessible via `jmeter --version` before creating the script</constraint>
      <constraint>**CRITICAL**: Copy the run-jmeter.sh template exactly — do not modify, interpret, or enhance</constraint>
      <constraint>**PERMISSION**: Make the script executable with `chmod +x run-jmeter.sh`</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for the exact script template and usage instructions</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If request scope is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before applying changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required inputs, files, or tooling are missing, report what is missing and ask whether to proceed with setup guidance</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Improve the code with JMeter performance testing</trigger>
        <trigger>Apply JMeter performance testing</trigger>
        <trigger>Refactor the code with JMeter performance testing</trigger>
        <trigger>Add JMeter support</trigger>
        <trigger>Create a JMeter test plan for a Java service</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Verify JMeter prerequisite</step-title>
      <step-content>Check `jmeter --version` and stop with guidance if JMeter is not installed or not available in PATH.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Read JMeter reference template</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/151-java-performance-jmeter.md` and use the `run-jmeter.sh` template exactly as provided.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Create script and project structure</step-title>
      <step-content>Create `run-jmeter.sh` in project root, ensure required JMeter directories/files exist, and apply executable permission with `chmod +x`.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Explain usage and environment overrides</step-title>
      <step-content>Document CLI options (`-l`, `-t`, `-r`, `-g`, `-h`) and environment variable overrides (`JMETER_LOOPS`, `JMETER_THREADS`, `JMETER_RAMP_UP`).</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
