<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="162-java-profiling-analyze">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.16.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to analyze Java profiling data collected during the detection phase — including interpreting flamegraphs, memory allocation patterns, CPU hotspots, threading issues, systematic problem categorization, evidence documentation with profiling-problem-analysis and profiling-solutions markdown files, or prioritizing fixes using Impact/Effort scoring. This should trigger for requests such as Analyze JFR profile; Analyze the profile; Analyze the performance; Analyze the memory.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Java Profiling Workflow / Step 2 / Analyze profiling data</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Analyze profiling results systematically: inventory results (flamegraphs, JFR, GC logs, thread dumps), identify problems (memory leaks, CPU hotspots, threading issues), document findings using standardized templates (profiling-problem-analysis-YYYYMMDD.md, profiling-solutions-YYYYMMDD.md), prioritize using Impact/Effort scores, and correlate multiple profiling files for validation.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Inventory: scan profiler/results/ for allocation-flamegraph, heatmap-cpu, memory-leak, *.jfr, *.log, *.txt
- Problem identification: memory (leaks, excessive allocations, GC pressure), performance (CPU hotspots, blocking), threading (deadlocks, contention, pool saturation)
- Documentation: docs/profiling-problem-analysis-YYYYMMDD.md, docs/profiling-solutions-YYYYMMDD.md
- Prioritization: Impact (1–5) / Effort (1–5), focus on high priority first
- Tools: async-profiler, JFR, JProfiler/YourKit, GCViewer, flamegraphs, heatmaps

**Scope:** Validate profiling results represent realistic load scenarios. Cross-reference multiple files. Include quantitative metrics.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Validate profiling results represent realistic load before analysis. Document assumptions and limitations. Cross-reference multiple files.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**VALIDATE**: Ensure profiling results represent realistic load scenarios before analysis</constraint>
      <constraint>**DOCUMENT**: Record assumptions and limitations in analysis reports</constraint>
      <constraint>**CROSS-REFERENCE**: Use multiple profiling files to validate findings</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for problem analysis and solutions templates</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If request scope is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before applying changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required inputs, files, or tooling are missing, report what is missing and ask whether to proceed with setup guidance</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Analyze JFR profile</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the profile</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the performance</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the memory</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the threading</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the GC</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the profiling</trigger>
        <trigger>Analyze the profiling</trigger>
        <trigger>Performance analysis</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Read analysis reference and inventory inputs</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/162-java-profiling-analyze.md` and inventory profiling artifacts in `profiler/results/`.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Validate data quality and assumptions</step-title>
      <step-content>Confirm datasets represent realistic load conditions and record assumptions/limitations before drawing conclusions.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Identify and prioritize bottlenecks</step-title>
      <step-content>Analyze memory/CPU/threading findings, cross-reference multiple files, and prioritize issues by Impact/Effort.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Document findings and solution options</step-title>
      <step-content>Create `docs/profiling-problem-analysis-YYYYMMDD.md` and `docs/profiling-solutions-YYYYMMDD.md` with quantitative evidence.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
