<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="200-agents-md"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.17.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to generate an AGENTS.md file for a Java repository — covering project conventions, tech stack, file structure, commands, Git workflow, and contributor boundaries — through a modular, step-based interactive process that adapts to your specific project needs. This should trigger for requests such as Create AGENTS.md; Update AGENTS.md file; Add agent instructions.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>AGENTS.md Generator for Java repositories</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Generate a comprehensive AGENTS.md file for Java repositories through a modular, step-based interactive process that covers role definition, tech stack, file structure, commands, Git workflow, and contributor boundaries. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- AGENTS.md generation for Java repositories of any complexity
- Role and expertise definition for AI agents and contributors
- Tech stack documentation: language, build tool, frameworks, pipelines
- File structure mapping with read/write boundaries
- Command catalogue for build/test/deploy/run workflows
- Git workflow conventions: branching strategy, commit message format
- Contributor boundaries using ✅ Always do / ⚠ Ask first / 🚫 Never do formatting
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>No Maven validation is required before generating AGENTS.md. Review the project structure and existing documentation before starting to provide accurate answers during Step 1.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**BEFORE STARTING**: Review the project structure and existing documentation to provide accurate answers during Step 1</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed good/bad examples, constraints, and safeguards for each AGENTS.md generation pattern</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If the user goal is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before editing files or running project-wide commands</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required context, files, credentials, or tools are missing, report the blocker explicitly and ask whether to proceed with setup or fallback guidance</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If requested changes conflict with project constraints or safety boundaries, explain the conflict and ask for user confirmation on the preferred trade-off</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Create AGENTS.md</trigger>
        <trigger>Update AGENTS.md file</trigger>
        <trigger>Add agent instructions</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1">
      <step-title>Review repository context before drafting</step-title>
      <step-content>Inspect project structure and existing documentation to prepare accurate responses for the AGENTS.md discovery phase.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="2">
      <step-title>Read AGENTS generation reference</step-title>
      <step-content>Read `references/200-agents-md.md` and follow its generation patterns and safeguards.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="3">
      <step-title>Run interactive requirements capture</step-title>
      <step-content>Gather role, tech stack, commands, workflow, and boundaries in a modular step-based conversation.</step-content>
    </step>
    <step number="4">
      <step-title>Generate AGENTS.md artifact</step-title>
      <step-content>Create AGENTS.md with ✅ Always do / ⚠ Ask first / 🚫 Never do boundaries and repository-specific conventions.</step-content>
    </step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
