<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="316-frameworks-spring-mongodb-migrations-mongock">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to add or review Mongock MongoDB data migrations in a Spring Boot application — including Maven coordinates, Spring Data MongoDB drivers, migration scan packages, @ChangeUnit classes, lock/transaction settings, and optional policy-approved MongoDB integration verification. This should trigger for requests such as Add Mongock migrations in Spring Boot; Review Spring MongoDB data migrations; Configure Mongock change units for Spring Data MongoDB; Create Mongock change units for Spring Boot MongoDB; Review Mongock migration ordering in a Spring service.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Spring - MongoDB migrations (Mongock)</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Apply Mongock migration guidelines for Spring Boot and Spring Data MongoDB.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Mongock BOM, Spring Boot runner, and Spring Data MongoDB driver coordinates
- `mongock.migration-scan-package` configuration and startup execution
- Code-first `@ChangeUnit` migrations with `@Execution` and rollback hooks
- Locking, idempotency, transaction limits, and forward-only rollout discipline
- Optional MongoDB-backed integration tests using only project-approved, pinned, or already-available container images when the user permits external runtime dependencies
- Coordination with `@315-frameworks-spring-mongodb`

**Scope:** Apply recommendations based on the reference rules and good/bad examples.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Compile before Mongock or MongoDB migration changes; verify after changes.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before applying any change</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If compilation fails, stop immediately</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed rules and good/bad patterns</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If the project Spring Data MongoDB version is not compatible with the selected Mongock driver, stop and ask whether to pin/upgrade Mongock or use a lower driver generation</constraint>
      <constraint>**EXTERNAL RUNTIME GATE**: Do not pull or execute Docker images for MongoDB verification unless the user explicitly approves and the image is pinned, policy-approved, or already present in the project configuration</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Add Mongock migrations in Spring Boot</trigger>
        <trigger>Review Spring MongoDB data migrations</trigger>
        <trigger>Configure Mongock change units for Spring Data MongoDB</trigger>
        <trigger>Create Mongock change units for Spring Boot MongoDB</trigger>
        <trigger>Review Mongock migration ordering in a Spring service</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <steps>
    <step number="1"><step-title>Read references and inspect MongoDB setup</step-title><step-content>Read `references/316-frameworks-spring-mongodb-migrations-mongock.md`, `references/316-frameworks-spring-mongodb-migrations-mongock-antipatterns.md`, and `references/316-frameworks-spring-mongodb-migrations-mongock-parallel-change.md`, then inspect `pom.xml`, Spring Boot version, dependency management, MongoDB configuration, existing full-context tests, and existing `@315-frameworks-spring-mongodb` persistence patterns.</step-content></step>
    <step number="2"><step-title>Choose runner, driver, and execution policy</step-title><step-content>Select Mongock coordinates compatible with the active Spring Data MongoDB generation, configure migration scan packages, and decide startup vs controlled-job execution.</step-content></step>
    <step number="3"><step-title>Apply framework-aligned migrations</step-title><step-content>Implement/refactor `@ChangeUnit` classes with idempotent operations, explicit ordering, rollback hooks, and safe lock/transaction settings.</step-content></step>
    <step number="4"><step-title>Run verification and report results</step-title><step-content>Execute build/tests. Run MongoDB-backed migration checks only when the project already defines an approved MongoDB test runtime or the user explicitly approves a pinned container image. If generic `@SpringBootTest` smoke tests do not provide MongoDB, disable Mongock only for those tests with `mongock.enabled=false`. Summarize outcomes and follow-up risks.</step-content></step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
