<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="502-frameworks-micronaut-rest">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to design, review, or improve REST APIs with Micronaut — including @Controller routes, HTTP status codes, DTOs, Bean Validation, exception handlers, pagination, idempotency, ETag/If-Match, caching headers, versioning, contract-first OpenAPI (OpenAPI Generator), optional runtime OpenAPI via micronaut-openapi, and security annotations. This should trigger for requests such as Review or improve Micronaut @Controller REST APIs; Add validation, error handling, or align controllers with the OpenAPI contract on Micronaut HTTP layer; Design Micronaut controllers and DTO validation; Add Micronaut exception handlers and Problem Details responses; Improve pagination filtering or OpenAPI alignment in Micronaut APIs.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Micronaut REST API Guidelines</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Apply REST design principles for Micronaut HTTP applications.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Semantic HTTP with @Get/@Post/@Put/@Patch/@Delete and HttpResponse status control
- Resource-oriented paths and stable DTO contracts
- @Valid on request bodies with Bean Validation
- Centralized error mapping (ExceptionHandler / problem JSON when applicable)
- Pagination with Pageable and bounded sizes
- OpenAPI contract file (API-first) and OpenAPI Generator for server stubs
- Security annotations (@Secured) on sensitive routes
- Idempotency-Key for retried writes
- ETag / If-Match for optimistic concurrency
- Cache-Control discipline
- API versioning patterns
- ISO-8601 time types in DTOs

**Scope:** Apply recommendations based on the reference rules and good/bad code examples.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Compile before REST refactors; verify after.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before applying any change</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If compilation fails, stop immediately</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed rules and examples</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If request scope is ambiguous, stop and ask a clarifying question before applying changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**EDGE CASE**: If required inputs, files, or tooling are missing, report what is missing and ask whether to proceed with setup guidance</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Review or improve Micronaut @Controller REST APIs</trigger>
        <trigger>Add validation, error handling, or align controllers with the OpenAPI contract on Micronaut HTTP layer</trigger>
        <trigger>Design Micronaut controllers and DTO validation</trigger>
        <trigger>Add Micronaut exception handlers and Problem Details responses</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve pagination filtering or OpenAPI alignment in Micronaut APIs</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>
  <steps>
    <step number="1"><step-title>Read reference and assess project context</step-title><step-content>Read `references/502-frameworks-micronaut-rest.md` and inspect the current project setup before proposing changes.</step-content></step>
    <step number="2"><step-title>Gather scope and decide target improvements</step-title><step-content>Identify requested outcomes, constraints, and the minimum safe set of changes to apply.</step-content></step>
    <step number="3"><step-title>Apply framework-aligned changes</step-title><step-content>Implement or refactor configuration/code following the reference patterns and project conventions.</step-content></step>
    <step number="4"><step-title>Run verification and report results</step-title><step-content>Execute appropriate build/tests and summarize what changed, what was verified, and any follow-up actions.</step-content></step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
