<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd"
      id="511-frameworks-micronaut-jdbc">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need programmatic JDBC in Micronaut — pooled DataSource, parameterized SQL, io.micronaut.transaction.annotation.Transactional, batching, and domain exception translation. This should trigger for requests such as Review JDBC or SQL data access in a Micronaut project; Improve transactions and parameter binding for Micronaut JDBC; Translate SQLException to domain exceptions or stream large result sets; Fix self-invocation bypassing @Transactional in Micronaut; Review Hikari or pooled datasource usage in Micronaut JDBC.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Micronaut JDBC — programmatic SQL</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Apply programmatic JDBC patterns in Micronaut with safe SQL and clear transactions.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- Injected javax.sql.DataSource (Hikari-backed with micronaut-jdbc-hikari) and try-with-resources for Connection / PreparedStatement
- PreparedStatement with bind parameters — never string concatenation
- Mapping ResultSet rows to Java records (dedicated mapRow method)
- Safe single-row queries with Optional<T>; never assume rs.next() succeeds
- SQLException translation to domain exceptions (catch-translate-rethrow)
- Streaming large result sets with setFetchSize to avoid OOM
- Batch updates with addBatch / executeBatch for bulk inserts
- @Transactional service boundaries and TransactionDefinition.Propagation (e.g. REQUIRES_NEW for independent commits)
- Self-invocation pitfall: call transactional collaborators through injected beans, not this.method()
- SQL text blocks for multi-line SQL (upserts, dialect-specific clauses)
- When to prefer Micronaut Data (`@512`) vs raw JDBC

**Scope:** Apply recommendations based on the reference rules and good/bad code examples.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Compile before JDBC refactors; verify after changes.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before applying any change</constraint>
      <constraint>**PREREQUISITE**: Project must compile before applying JDBC improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If compilation fails, stop immediately</constraint>
      <constraint>**BLOCKING CONDITION**: Compilation errors must be resolved by the user before proceeding</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed rules and examples</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Review JDBC or SQL data access in a Micronaut project</trigger>
        <trigger>Improve transactions and parameter binding for Micronaut JDBC</trigger>
        <trigger>Translate SQLException to domain exceptions or stream large result sets</trigger>
        <trigger>Fix self-invocation bypassing @Transactional in Micronaut</trigger>
        <trigger>Review Hikari or pooled datasource usage in Micronaut JDBC</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>
  <steps>
    <step number="1"><step-title>Read reference and assess project context</step-title><step-content>Read `references/511-frameworks-micronaut-jdbc.md` and inspect the current project setup before proposing changes.</step-content></step>
    <step number="2"><step-title>Gather scope and decide target improvements</step-title><step-content>Identify requested outcomes, constraints, and the minimum safe set of changes to apply.</step-content></step>
    <step number="3"><step-title>Apply framework-aligned changes</step-title><step-content>Implement or refactor configuration/code following the reference patterns and project conventions.</step-content></step>
    <step number="4"><step-title>Run verification and report results</step-title><step-content>Execute appropriate build/tests and summarize what changed, what was verified, and any follow-up actions.</step-content></step>
  </steps>
</prompt>
