<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="111-java-maven-dependencies"
      interactive="true">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.13.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to add or evaluate Maven dependencies that improve code quality — including nullness annotations (JSpecify), static analysis (Error Prone + NullAway), functional programming (VAVR), or architecture testing (ArchUnit) — and want a consultative, question-driven approach that adds only what you actually need.</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Add Maven dependencies for improved code quality</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Add essential Maven dependencies that enhance code quality and safety through a consultative, question-driven approach. **This is an interactive SKILL**.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- JSpecify: (nullness annotations, `provided` scope)
- Error Prone + NullAway: (enhanced static analysis with compile-time null checking)
- VAVR: (functional programming with Try/Either and immutable collections)
- ArchUnit: (architecture rule enforcement, `test` scope)
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Before adding Maven dependencies, ensure the project is in a valid state. Use a consultative, question-driven flow that adds only what the user selects.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw validate` or `mvn validate` before any changes</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If validation fails, stop and ask the user to fix issues—do not proceed until resolved</constraint>
      <constraint><![CDATA[**BEFORE ASKING QUESTIONS**: Read the reference to use the exact wording and options from the template. Ask questions one-by-one in strict order (JSpecify → Enhanced Compiler Analysis (conditional) → VAVR → ArchUnit) and add only what the user selects. Use consultative language, present trade-offs, and wait for user responses before implementing]]></constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Add Maven dependencies</trigger>
        <trigger>JSpecify nullness</trigger>
        <trigger>Error Prone NullAway</trigger>
        <trigger>VAVR functional</trigger>
        <trigger>ArchUnit architecture testing</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <references>
    <reference-list>
        <reference>references/111-java-maven-dependencies.md</reference>
    </reference-list>
  </references>
</prompt>
