<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.7.0/pml.xsd"
      id="422-frameworks-quarkus-testing-integration-tests">
  <metadata>
    <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
    <version>0.13.0</version>
    <license>Apache-2.0</license>
    <description>Use when you need to write or improve integration tests for Quarkus — including @QuarkusTest, Dev Services for automatic container provisioning, Testcontainers via QuarkusTestResourceLifecycleManager, WireMock for external HTTP stubs, @QuarkusIntegrationTest for black-box testing against packaged artifacts, REST Assured, data isolation strategies (@TestTransaction vs @BeforeEach cleanup), and Maven Surefire/Failsafe three-tier split (*Test, *IT, *AT).</description>
  </metadata>

  <title>Quarkus integration testing</title>
  <goal><![CDATA[
Apply integration testing patterns for Quarkus with real wiring and reproducible infrastructure.

**What is covered in this Skill?**

- @QuarkusTest for in-JVM integration with real CDI wiring
- Dev Services for automatic container provisioning (%test.quarkus.datasource.devservices)
- Testcontainers via QuarkusTestResourceLifecycleManager (start/stop lifecycle, dynamic config injection)
- WireMock for stubbing external HTTP services via QuarkusTestResourceLifecycleManager
- @QuarkusIntegrationTest for black-box testing against the packaged JAR or native binary
- HTTP testing with REST Assured against the Quarkus test port
- Data isolation: @TestTransaction for automatic rollback; @BeforeEach cleanup for HTTP tests
- Maven three-tier split: *Test → Surefire (fast), *IT + *AT → Failsafe (verify)
- Native-image test considerations with @DisabledOnNativeImage

**Scope:** Apply recommendations based on the reference rules and good/bad code examples.
]]></goal>

  <constraints>
    <constraints-description>Compile before changes; verify after; Docker may be required for containers.</constraints-description>
    <constraint-list>
      <constraint>**MANDATORY**: Run `./mvnw compile` or `mvn compile` before applying any change</constraint>
      <constraint>**PREREQUISITE**: Project must compile before applying integration test improvements</constraint>
      <constraint>**SAFETY**: If compilation fails, stop immediately</constraint>
      <constraint>**BLOCKING CONDITION**: Compilation errors must be resolved by the user before proceeding</constraint>
      <constraint>**VERIFY**: Run `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify` after applying improvements; Docker is required for Testcontainers and Dev Services</constraint>
      <constraint>**BEFORE APPLYING**: Read the reference for detailed rules and examples</constraint>
    </constraint-list>
  </constraints>

  <triggers>
    <trigger-list>
        <trigger>Add or improve integration tests in a Quarkus project</trigger>
        <trigger>Configure Testcontainers or Dev Services for Quarkus tests</trigger>
        <trigger>Add WireMock stubs for external HTTP dependencies in Quarkus integration tests</trigger>
        <trigger>Set up @QuarkusIntegrationTest for packaged artifact or native binary testing</trigger>
        <trigger>Fix test data isolation or configure Maven Surefire/Failsafe split</trigger>
    </trigger-list>
  </triggers>

  <references>
    <reference-list>
        <reference>references/422-frameworks-quarkus-testing-integration-tests.md</reference>
    </reference-list>
  </references>
</prompt>
