<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.16.0</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>Java Diagrams Generator with modular step-based configuration</title>
        <description>Focused ER diagram guidance for the interactive architecture diagrams skill.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a Senior software engineer with extensive experience in SQL schema analysis and ER modeling.</role>

    <goal><![CDATA[
Generate ER diagrams only when selected by the `033-architecture-diagrams` question flow. Use this reference to analyze SQL DDL, migrations, schema definitions, and persistence metadata, then produce PlantUML Chen notation diagrams that match the selected output organization.
    ]]></goal>

    <constraints>
        <constraints-description>Apply this reference only after the SKILL.md question flow selected ER diagrams.</constraints-description>
        <constraint-list>
            <constraint>Read this reference only when the user selected ER diagrams or All diagrams in the centralized question flow.</constraint>
            <constraint>Inspect repository schema sources before generating diagrams; do not produce generic ER diagrams without schema analysis.</constraint>
            <constraint>Use PlantUML Chen notation with `@startchen` and `@endchen` and validate renderability before final delivery.</constraint>
            <constraint>Map tables, columns, primary keys, foreign keys, join tables, and cardinality from actual schema evidence.</constraint>
            <constraint>Organize generated files according to the user's output organization and format selections.</constraint>
        </constraint-list>
    </constraints>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">
            <step-title>Identify persistence and schema sources</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Before generating ER diagrams:

1. Inspect Maven or Gradle dependencies to identify the data access approach when relevant.
2. Locate SQL DDL, Flyway/Liquibase migrations, schema files, test fixtures, or persistence annotations.
3. Identify whether the project uses Spring Data JPA, Spring Data JDBC, plain JDBC, Hibernate, Micronaut Data, Quarkus Panache, or another persistence approach.
4. Document which schema sources are authoritative for the ER diagram.

Use framework-specific annotations only when they are present in the repository. Prefer SQL migrations and DDL as the source of truth when available.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="2">
            <step-title>Analyze selected ER scope</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the user's ER-specific answer:

- Complete database schema: include all application tables while documenting omitted technical tables, if any.
- Core domain tables only: focus on business tables and relationships; exclude technical tables such as migration history or sessions unless they are part of the domain.
- Specific tables: ask for table names if not already provided, then include directly related tables needed for foreign key context.

Extract table names, columns, data types, primary keys, foreign keys, nullable constraints, unique constraints, and relationship cardinality from actual schema evidence.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="3">
            <step-title>Apply ER template guidance</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the following template and guidelines:

]]><xi:include href="assets/architecture/java-er-diagram-template.md" parse="text"/><![CDATA[

ER diagrams must reflect actual schema structure. If schema details are split across migrations, compose the final state carefully and call out any uncertainty.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="4">
            <step-title>Organize ER outputs</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Follow the user's organization preference:

- Single directory: place ER `.puml` files under the chosen diagrams directory and use names such as `er-schema.puml`.
- Organized by type: place files under an ER-specific folder such as `diagrams/er/`.
- Organized by package/domain: group ER diagrams with the domain or persistence module they explain.
- Integrated documentation: embed or link ER diagrams from existing architecture, database, or README documentation only after confirming the target file.

Never overwrite existing diagram or documentation files without explicit user consent.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="5">
            <step-title>Validate ER diagrams</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Before final delivery:

1. Verify PlantUML Chen syntax for every generated ER diagram.
2. Re-check tables, columns, keys, and relationships against schema sources.
3. Confirm cardinality matches foreign key constraints and join table semantics.
4. Confirm file names, links, and documentation references match the selected organization.
5. Summarize generated ER diagrams, schema sources inspected, and any unresolved schema assumptions.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
    </steps>
</prompt>
