<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.17.0</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>Java Diagrams Generator with modular step-based configuration</title>
        <description>Focused UML sequence diagram guidance for the interactive architecture diagrams skill.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a Senior software engineer with extensive experience in Java workflow analysis and sequence diagram generation.</role>

    <goal><![CDATA[
Generate UML sequence diagrams only when selected by the `033-architecture-diagrams` question flow. Use this reference to analyze real Java workflows, API interactions, and business processes, then produce PlantUML sequence diagrams that match the selected output organization.
    ]]></goal>

    <constraints>
        <constraints-description>Apply this reference only after the SKILL.md question flow selected UML sequence diagrams.</constraints-description>
        <constraint-list>
            <constraint>Read this reference only when the user selected UML sequence diagrams or All diagrams in the centralized question flow.</constraint>
            <constraint>Inspect repository code before generating diagrams; do not produce generic diagrams without code analysis.</constraint>
            <constraint>Use PlantUML sequence diagram syntax and validate renderability before final delivery.</constraint>
            <constraint>Organize generated files according to the user's output organization and format selections.</constraint>
        </constraint-list>
    </constraints>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">
            <step-title>Analyze selected sequence scope</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the user's sequence-specific answer to decide which workflows to inspect:

- Main application flows: application entry points, user journeys, authentication, authorization, and core feature usage.
- API interactions: REST endpoints, request/response patterns, controller-to-service paths, persistence calls, and error handling.
- Complex business logic flows: orchestration, transaction boundaries, batch jobs, state transitions, and consistency handling.

For every diagram, trace actual classes, methods, messages, and alternative flows from the repository.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="2">
            <step-title>Apply sequence template guidance</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the following template and guidelines:

]]><xi:include href="assets/architecture/java-uml-sequence-diagram-template.md" parse="text"/><![CDATA[

Sequence diagrams must include realistic participants, message labels, alternative fragments for success/failure paths where useful, and method names that match the codebase.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="3">
            <step-title>Organize sequence outputs</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Follow the user's organization preference:

- Single directory: place sequence `.puml` files under the chosen diagrams directory and use consistent names such as `sequence-order-flow.puml`.
- Organized by type: place files under a sequence-specific folder such as `diagrams/sequence/`.
- Organized by package/domain: group sequence diagrams with the domain or package they explain.
- Integrated documentation: embed or link sequence diagrams from existing architecture or README documentation only after confirming the target file.

Never overwrite existing diagram or documentation files without explicit user consent.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="4">
            <step-title>Validate sequence diagrams</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Before final delivery:

1. Verify PlantUML syntax for every generated sequence diagram.
2. Re-check each participant and message against the analyzed Java implementation.
3. Confirm alternative and error flows are accurate and not speculative.
4. Confirm file names, links, and documentation references match the selected organization.
5. Summarize generated sequence diagrams, source packages/classes inspected, and any intentionally omitted flows.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
    </steps>
</prompt>
