<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="https://jabrena.github.io/pml/schemas/0.8.0/pml.xsd">
    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.18.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>Java Diagrams Generator with modular step-based configuration</title>
        <description>Focused UML state machine diagram guidance for the interactive architecture diagrams skill.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a Senior software engineer with extensive experience in Java workflow, lifecycle, and state modeling.</role>

    <goal><![CDATA[
Generate UML state machine diagrams only when selected by the `033-architecture-diagrams` question flow. Use this reference to analyze real entity lifecycles, business workflows, system behaviors, and user interaction states, then produce PlantUML state diagrams that match the selected output organization.
    ]]></goal>

    <constraints>
        <constraints-description>Apply this reference only after the SKILL.md question flow selected UML state-machine diagrams.</constraints-description>
        <constraint-list>
            <constraint>Read this reference only when the user selected UML state-machine diagrams or All diagrams in the centralized question flow.</constraint>
            <constraint>Inspect repository code before generating diagrams; do not produce generic state diagrams without lifecycle or workflow analysis.</constraint>
            <constraint>Use PlantUML state machine syntax and validate renderability before final delivery.</constraint>
            <constraint>Include guards, triggers, actions, initial states, final states, and error states only when supported by repository evidence.</constraint>
            <constraint>Organize generated files according to the user's output organization and format selections.</constraint>
        </constraint-list>
    </constraints>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">
            <step-title>Analyze selected state scope</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the user's state-machine-specific answer:

- Entity lifecycles: analyze domain entities, enum states, state-changing methods, validation rules, and terminal states.
- Business workflows: analyze approval, payment, shipping, provisioning, background job, or other process orchestration paths.
- System behaviors: analyze connection, job, transaction, retry, timeout, and recovery states in infrastructure components.
- User interactions: analyze form, wizard, dialog, navigation, and validation states when UI sources exist.

Reference actual enum values, method names, classes, commands, events, and guards from the repository.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="2">
            <step-title>Apply state template guidance</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Use the following template and guidelines:

]]><xi:include href="assets/architecture/java-uml-state-machine-diagram-template.md" parse="text"/><![CDATA[

State diagrams must reflect actual lifecycle and transition rules. If a lifecycle is implied but not implemented, clearly label it as an inferred candidate and ask for confirmation before generating final files.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="3">
            <step-title>Organize state outputs</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Follow the user's organization preference:

- Single directory: place state `.puml` files under the chosen diagrams directory and use names such as `state-order-lifecycle.puml`.
- Organized by type: place files under a state-specific folder such as `diagrams/state-machine/`.
- Organized by package/domain: group state diagrams with the entity, workflow, or component they explain.
- Integrated documentation: embed or link state diagrams from existing architecture, domain, or README documentation only after confirming the target file.

Never overwrite existing diagram or documentation files without explicit user consent.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="4">
            <step-title>Validate state diagrams</step-title>
            <step-content><![CDATA[
Before final delivery:

1. Verify PlantUML syntax for every generated state machine diagram.
2. Re-check states, transitions, guards, actions, and terminal conditions against repository evidence.
3. Confirm business rules and exceptional paths are accurate.
4. Confirm file names, links, and documentation references match the selected organization.
5. Summarize generated state diagrams, classes/enums/workflows inspected, and any unresolved lifecycle assumptions.
            ]]></step-content>
        </step>
    </steps>
</prompt>
