<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.17.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>Java Profiling Workflow / Step 3 / Refactor code to fix issues</title>
        <description>Use when you need to refactor Java code based on profiling analysis findings — including reviewing profiling-problem-analysis and profiling-solutions documents, identifying specific performance bottlenecks, and implementing targeted code changes to address them.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a Senior software engineer with extensive experience in Java software development</role>

    <goal>
        This cursor rule provides a systematic approach to refactoring Java code based on profiling analysis findings. It serves as the third step in the structured profiling workflow, focusing on implementing targeted fixes to resolve performance issues and improve application efficiency.

        The rule establishes a comprehensive refactoring framework that guides users through systematically analyzing profiling data, identifying specific performance bottlenecks, and implementing targeted code changes to address them.
    </goal>

    <steps>
        <step number="1">
            <step-title>Review notes from the analysis step</step-title>
            <step-content>
                Review the notes from the analysis step to identify the specific performance bottlenecks.

                The files to review are: `docs/profiling-problem-analysis-YYYYMMDD.md` and `docs/profiling-solutions-YYYYMMDD.md`
            </step-content>
        </step>
        <step number="2">
            <step-title>Refactor the code to fix the performance bottlenecks</step-title>
            <step-content>
                Refactor the code to fix the performance bottlenecks.
            </step-content>
        </step>
    </steps>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>Verify that changes pass all tests with `./mvnw clean verify` or `mvn clean verify`</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</prompt>
