<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prompt xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <metadata>
        <author>Juan Antonio Breña Moral</author>
        <version>0.16.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
        <license>Apache-2.0</license>
        <title>EU Digital Omnibus Proposal Impact Review for Java Enterprise Systems</title>
        <description>Use as Java-focused Digital Omnibus engineering examples for source-status checks, affected-regulation mapping, evidence inventory updates, change-control impacts, report-template updates, incident-reporting consolidation, data-rights impacts, AI governance timelines, and compatibility with existing EU regulation skills.</description>
    </metadata>

    <role>You are a senior Java enterprise architect and regulatory-change engineering reviewer who translates Digital Omnibus proposal-stage simplification themes into concrete Java engineering examples and reviewable evidence patterns</role>

    <goal>
        Apply these Digital Omnibus-aware examples after the source-status summary has been read and the target system scope is understood.

        These examples are not legal advice. They show engineering patterns that help Java teams create reviewable evidence for legal, compliance, privacy, security, risk, resilience, data-governance, AI governance, business, and executive accountability owners.

        Use this examples reference together with `references/809-regulations-eu-digital-omnibus-source-summary.md` and the [Digital Omnibus engineering review report template](../assets/reports/809-eu-digital-omnibus-engineering-review-report-template.md).
    </goal>

    <constraints>
        <constraints-description>
            Translate Digital Omnibus proposal-stage simplification concerns into engineering controls for Java enterprise systems without replacing qualified legal, compliance, privacy, security, risk, resilience, data-governance, AI governance, business, or executive accountability review.
        </constraints-description>
        <constraint-list>
            <constraint>**NOT LEGAL ADVICE**: Treat the examples as engineering control patterns and escalation aids, not legal findings</constraint>
            <constraint>**SOURCE STATUS BEFORE CHANGE**: Require source-status evidence before updating workflows, questionnaires, report templates, release gates, or governance timelines</constraint>
            <constraint>**EVIDENCE FIRST**: Prefer reviewable evidence over claims that simplification applies</constraint>
            <constraint>**OWNER HANDOFFS**: Include legal, compliance, privacy, security, risk, resilience, data-governance, AI governance, service, platform, and product owners in change records</constraint>
            <constraint>**NO AUTOMATIC CONTROL REDUCTION**: Do not mark a system ready when control relaxation, reporting consolidation, data-rights changes, or AI governance timeline changes are undocumented, unapproved, or source-status ambiguous</constraint>
        </constraint-list>
    </constraints>

    <examples>
        <toc auto-generate="true" />

        <example number="1" id="source-status-and-affected-regulation-map">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Record source status before recommending changes</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>official sources, status owner, affected regulations, and review date</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern before updating a Java platform's compliance evidence, questionnaires, runbooks, release gates, or regulation-skill outputs. The record makes proposal-stage assumptions visible and prevents teams from treating simplification as adopted law without owner approval.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="yaml"><![CDATA[digitalOmnibusSourceStatus:
  reviewDate: 2026-06-14
  sourceStatusOwner: legal-compliance
  sources:
    - title: European Commission news - simpler digital rules
      url: https://commission.europa.eu/news-and-media/news/simpler-digital-rules-help-eu-businesses-grow-2025-11-19_en
      statusObserved: official Commission communication about simplification proposals
    - title: An agile Digital Rulebook for the EU
      url: https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/digital-rulebook
      statusObserved: November Digital Omnibus proposal discussed by co-legislators
  affectedRegulations:
    - AI Act: high-risk obligation timing and governance oversight require AI governance review
    - GDPR/ePrivacy: privacy evidence and data-rights workflows require privacy owner review
    - NIS2/DORA: incident-reporting consolidation requires security and resilience owner review
    - Data Act/data acquis: data access and sharing records require data-governance review
  decision: no-control-relaxation-without-qualified-owner-approval]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="yaml"><![CDATA[digitalOmnibusSourceStatus:
  status: omnibus simplifies everything
  decision: remove old reporting controls]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="2" id="evidence-inventory-update">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Update evidence inventory with traceable change candidates</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>policies, reports, runbooks, dashboards, owners, and release gates</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern when a Java service has existing GDPR, DORA, NIS2, AI Act, privacy, cybersecurity, data-governance, or resilience evidence. Digital Omnibus review should identify update candidates and owner handoffs, not silently rewrite records.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public DigitalOmnibusEvidencePlan planEvidenceUpdates(DigitalOmnibusReview review) {
    List<EvidenceUpdateCandidate> candidates = List.of(
        EvidenceUpdateCandidate.forArtifact("incident-runbook")
            .affectedArea("NIS2/DORA incident-reporting workflow")
            .sourceStatus(review.sourceStatus())
            .owner("security-operations")
            .requiredDecision("confirm whether single-entry reporting can be adopted"),
        EvidenceUpdateCandidate.forArtifact("privacy-rights-workflow")
            .affectedArea("GDPR/ePrivacy data-rights workflow")
            .sourceStatus(review.sourceStatus())
            .owner("privacy-owner")
            .requiredDecision("confirm whether workflow wording changes are approved"),
        EvidenceUpdateCandidate.forArtifact("ai-governance-roadmap")
            .affectedArea("AI Act timeline and standards dependency")
            .sourceStatus(review.sourceStatus())
            .owner("ai-governance-owner")
            .requiredDecision("confirm timeline impact before release plan changes")
    );

    return DigitalOmnibusEvidencePlan.requiresOwnerReview(review.serviceId(), candidates);
}]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public void updateEvidence() {
    complianceRepository.deleteOldQuestions();
}]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="3" id="change-control-impact-review">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Gate releases that depend on proposed simplification</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>release decision, owner approval, source status, and control compatibility</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern when a release, migration, feature flag, AI workflow, incident workflow, or data-rights change assumes a Digital Omnibus simplification will apply. The release gate should block unapproved simplification-based changes.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public ReleaseDecision evaluateDigitalOmnibusAssumption(ReleaseEvidence evidence) {
    List<String> blockers = new ArrayList<>();

    requirePresent(evidence.digitalOmnibusSourceStatus(), "Digital Omnibus source-status record", blockers);
    requirePresent(evidence.affectedRegulationMap(), "affected-regulation mapping", blockers);
    requireApproved(evidence.legalStatusDecision(), "qualified legal/compliance status decision", blockers);
    requireApproved(evidence.controlRelaxationDecision(), "approved decision before any control relaxation", blockers);
    requirePassing(evidence.regulationSkillCompatibilityCheck(), "compatibility with 801-804 regulation-skill outputs", blockers);

    if (!blockers.isEmpty()) {
        return ReleaseDecision.blocked(
            evidence.serviceId(),
            blockers,
            Escalation.required("legal", "compliance", "privacy", "security", "risk", "ai-governance")
        );
    }

    return ReleaseDecision.approvedWithEvidence(evidence.serviceId(), evidence.references(), evidence.approvers());
}]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public ReleaseDecision evaluateDigitalOmnibusAssumption(ReleaseEvidence evidence) {
    return ReleaseDecision.approved(evidence.serviceId(), "Digital Omnibus will simplify this soon");
}]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="4" id="questionnaire-and-report-template-update-candidates">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Propose questionnaire and report-template updates safely</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>candidate list, source link, affected area, and owner decision</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern when existing questionnaires or report templates ask duplicated, obsolete, or potentially retimed questions. Mark updates as candidates until qualified owners approve the source interpretation and adoption path.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="markdown"><![CDATA[Questionnaire and report-template update candidates

| Artifact | Candidate update | Affected regulation area | Official source link | Required owner decision |
| -------- | ---------------- | ------------------------ | -------------------- | ----------------------- |
| DORA incident report template | Add field for shared single-entry reporting reference, do not remove DORA-specific handoff fields yet | DORA / cybersecurity incident reporting | https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/digital-rulebook | Legal, resilience, security operations |
| GDPR engineering questionnaire | Add review question for Digital Omnibus privacy simplification status, do not weaken lawful-basis, transparency, data-subject-rights, or breach evidence | GDPR/ePrivacy | https://commission.europa.eu/news-and-media/news/simpler-digital-rules-help-eu-businesses-grow-2025-11-19_en | Privacy, legal, compliance |
| AI governance report | Add timeline-impact section linked to standards and support-tool availability, do not defer high-risk controls without AI governance approval | AI Act | https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/digital-rulebook | AI governance, legal, product owner |]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="markdown"><![CDATA[Template cleanup

- Delete DORA incident questions.
- Delete GDPR breach fields.
- Push AI checks to next year.]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="5" id="incident-reporting-and-data-rights-workflows">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Review incident-reporting and data-rights workflow impacts</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>single-entry reporting, privacy handoff, and no premature relaxation</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern when a Java platform has incident, breach, data-rights, privacy, DORA, or NIS2 workflows. Digital Omnibus may create consolidation candidates, but engineering must preserve existing handoffs until owner approval.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public WorkflowImpact assessWorkflowImpact(IncidentAndRightsWorkflow workflow) {
    return WorkflowImpact.builder()
        .sourceStatusRequired(true)
        .candidate("Evaluate single-entry incident reporting intake")
        .preserveExistingControl("NIS2 severity triage")
        .preserveExistingControl("DORA financial ICT incident handoff")
        .preserveExistingControl("GDPR personal-data breach assessment")
        .preserveExistingControl("data-subject rights request deadlines and evidence")
        .requiredOwners(List.of("security-operations", "privacy-owner", "resilience-owner", "legal-compliance"))
        .decision("consolidation-candidate-only-until-approved")
        .build();
}]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="java"><![CDATA[public WorkflowImpact assessWorkflowImpact(IncidentAndRightsWorkflow workflow) {
    workflow.disableDoraHandoff();
    workflow.disableGdprBreachReview();
    return WorkflowImpact.simplified();
}]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>

        <example number="6" id="ai-governance-timeline-and-existing-skill-compatibility">
            <example-header>
                <example-title>Check AI governance timeline changes against existing skill outputs</example-title>
                <example-subtitle>standards dependency, high-risk controls, and compatibility records</example-subtitle>
            </example-header>
            <example-description>
                <![CDATA[
                Use this pattern when a Java application uses AI, LLMs, AI agents, RAG, model-based decision support, or AI-assisted workflow automation and the team asks whether Digital Omnibus affects AI Act planning. Treat timeline changes as owner-reviewed planning assumptions.
                ]]>
            </example-description>
            <code-examples>
                <good-example>
                    <code-block language="yaml"><![CDATA[aiGovernanceTimelineReview:
  system: customer-support-rag-assistant
  existingSkillOutputs:
    - 801-regulations-eu-ai-act: risk classification and technical documentation controls
    - 803-regulations-gdpr: personal-data minimization and data-subject-rights controls
    - 804-regulations-eu-nis2: incident and cybersecurity evidence controls
  digitalOmnibusImpactCandidate:
    affectedArea: AI Act high-risk obligation timing and AI Office governance oversight
    sourceStatus: proposal-stage, owner confirmation required
    proposedAction: add timeline-impact note and standards-readiness dependency to roadmap
    controlsPreserved:
      - risk classification
      - technical documentation
      - human oversight
      - logging and monitoring
      - privacy evidence
      - incident escalation
  escalation:
    owners: [ai-governance, legal-compliance, privacy, security, product]
    reason: proposal-stage language affects planning but does not approve control relaxation]]></code-block>
                </good-example>
                <bad-example last-item="true">
                    <code-block language="yaml"><![CDATA[aiGovernanceTimelineReview:
  decision: high-risk AI controls no longer needed
  sourceStatus: assumed]]></code-block>
                </bad-example>
            </code-examples>
        </example>
    </examples>

    <output-format>
        <output-format-list>
            <output-format-item>**MATCH** the relevant example patterns: source-status mapping, evidence inventory update, change-control impact review, questionnaire or report-template update candidate, incident-reporting workflow consolidation, data-rights workflow impact, AI governance timeline review, or existing skill compatibility check</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**RECOMMEND** engineering controls: official source-status records, affected-regulation maps, owner approvals, evidence inventory updates, change-control gates, report-template update candidates, incident-reporting consolidation candidates, data-rights impact reviews, AI governance timeline reviews, compatibility checks with existing EU regulation skills, and ambiguity escalation</output-format-item>
            <output-format-item>**REPORT** conclusions and actions using `assets/reports/809-eu-digital-omnibus-engineering-review-report-template.md`, including review context, source-status record, affected regulation area, associated official source link, evidence from reviewed system, current status, required owner review, engineering action, residual risk, adoption decision, and validation steps</output-format-item>
        </output-format-list>
    </output-format>

    <safeguards>
        <safeguards-list>
            <safeguards-item>**PROPOSAL-STAGE EVIDENCE**: Do not accept undocumented claims that Digital Omnibus simplification applies; require official source-status records and qualified owner decisions</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**REGULATION-SPECIFIC COMPATIBILITY**: Preserve existing AI Act, GDPR, DORA, NIS2, privacy, cybersecurity, resilience, data-governance, incident, and AI governance controls until approved changes are recorded</safeguards-item>
            <safeguards-item>**AMBIGUITY HANDOFF**: When proposal language is unclear, contradictory, or incomplete, report ambiguity and route it to owners instead of choosing an engineering shortcut</safeguards-item>
        </safeguards-list>
    </safeguards>
</prompt>
